Guide to the NYU Abu Dhabi Capstone Archives AD.MC.004
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
- Social Sciences Division Projects, 2014-2019
  - Economics
    - Zhu, Weichen. Difference Between Veteran and Civilian Real Wage Distribution from 1980 to 2010 in the United States., 2015; 2015-0058 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2015-0058)
      Abstract: Veteran and civilian wage difference is an important topic in labor economics and public policy. This research seeks to answer two questions. First, is there a significant difference between veteran and civilian real wage from 1980 to 2010? Second, if there is, what are the potential reasons that can explain the real wage discrepancy? The empirical evidence reveals that veterans in fact earn higher real wage than civilians from 1980 to 2010. The fluctuation of the veteran real wage premium is correlated with shifting composition of veterans from different wars. Evidence regarding social work, working hours, and racial heterogeneity of veterans is insufficient to explain veterans' higher real wage than civilians.
      Wars; Workers; Veterans; Wages; United States of America
    - Ahmad, Emaan. Traditional Institutions or Geography: Determinants of HEalth Outcomes in Sierra Leone., 2016; 2016-0051; Sierra Leone is one of the poorest countries in the world with one of the weakest health systems and lowest health statistics. Traditional institutions play an important role in large parts of the developing world. In Sierra Leone, the Paramount Chief, in particular, performs many essential formal duties such as tax collection, public service provision etc. Geography also plays an important role in health outcomes as areas near big cities and roads have more access to health resources and health professionals. This paper studies the impact of the quality of traditional institutions and geography on Sierra Leone's health outcomes. I will use an instrumental variable strategy to make causal claims about traditional institutions' impact on health outcomes and I will argue that geography is exogenous to make causal claims about geography's impact on health outcomes. I find that quality of traditional institutions does not have a significant impact on health outcomes, contrary to results obtained by Acemoglu et al in 2013. Proximity to nearby roads also does not have an impact on health outcomes. Proximity to a big city, on the other hand, has a significant, negative effect on 3 of my 7 health outcomes. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0051)
      Sierra Leone is one of the poorest countries in the world with one of the weakest health systems and lowest health statistics. Traditional institutions play an important role in large parts of the developing world. In Sierra Leone, the Paramount Chief, in particular, performs many essential formal duties such as tax collection, public service provision etc. Geography also plays an important role in health outcomes as areas near big cities and roads have more access to health resources and health professionals. This paper studies the impact of the quality of traditional institutions and geography on Sierra Leone's health outcomes. I will use an instrumental variable strategy to make causal claims about traditional institutions' impact on health outcomes and I will argue that geography is exogenous to make causal claims about geography's impact on health outcomes. I find that quality of traditional institutions does not have a significant impact on health outcomes, contrary to results obtained by Acemoglu et al in 2013. Proximity to nearby roads also does not have an impact on health outcomes. Proximity to a big city, on the other hand, has a significant, negative effect on 3 of my 7 health outcomes.
    - Ayson, Tessa. Bargaining Over Risk: The Effect of Strategic Uncertainty On Fairness Concerns., 2016; 2016-0059; We study how social preferences are affected by the presence of risk in bargaining contexts. We use a modified dictator game to differentiate between two types of fairness concerns, ex ante (probability-based) and ex post (outcome-based), and observe whether preferences can be explained exclusively by one of these types. We also adapt this modified game to include strategic uncertainty, in order to investigate how giving decisions change when both players have bargaining power. We predict that a combination of ex ante and ex post fairness concerns will best explain subjects' giving decisions under risk and in the presence of strategic uncertainty. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0059)
      We study how social preferences are affected by the presence of risk in bargaining contexts. We use a modified dictator game to differentiate between two types of fairness concerns, ex ante (probability-based) and ex post (outcome-based), and observe whether preferences can be explained exclusively by one of these types. We also adapt this modified game to include strategic uncertainty, in order to investigate how giving decisions change when both players have bargaining power. We predict that a combination of ex ante and ex post fairness concerns will best explain subjects' giving decisions under risk and in the presence of strategic uncertainty.
    - Dikov, Momchil. "The Effect of Announcements Regarding Interest Rate Changes on Asset Trading and Price Bubbles"., 2016; 2016-0057; This paper studies the impact of interest rate change announcements on asset trading and price bubbles in experimental asset markets. The study employs an experimental limit order asset market, in which each participant is endowed with cash and dividend-paying assets (shares in our case) that can be traded in the market; the unused cash earns interest after trading in each period and dividends are paid on each share. We look at how the uncertainty about future interest rates impacts the trading price relative to the flat fundamental value of the share, as well as the trading volume. We compare the results in the treatment and the baseline groups after an announcement tells the subjects in the treatment groups how the interest rate will change. We find that the uncertainty regarding interest rate changes does not have an effect on the price bubbles, but significantly reduces the volume of trade. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0057)
      This paper studies the impact of interest rate change announcements on asset trading and price bubbles in experimental asset markets. The study employs an experimental limit order asset market, in which each participant is endowed with cash and dividend-paying assets (shares in our case) that can be traded in the market; the unused cash earns interest after trading in each period and dividends are paid on each share. We look at how the uncertainty about future interest rates impacts the trading price relative to the flat fundamental value of the share, as well as the trading volume. We compare the results in the treatment and the baseline groups after an announcement tells the subjects in the treatment groups how the interest rate will change. We find that the uncertainty regarding interest rate changes does not have an effect on the price bubbles, but significantly reduces the volume of trade.
    - Lukashenko, Yuliya. Paying for the Tag: The Effect of Luxury Brand Labels on Willingness to Pay., 2016; 2016-0060; In economics, many theories were proposed since Veblen's (1899) analysis of conspicuous consumption to better understand the mechanisms that allow luxury brands to charge high prices for their products. While luxury markets continue to grow all around the world, little experimental research has been done to support those theories. The purpose of this research is to identify whether a presence of a brand label on a luxury good affects willingness to pay. Contrary to hypothetical survey settings used previously on this topic, this experiment is designed to offer real life incentives for revealing the true value people attribute to a brand label with low brand prominence. Using lotteries to elicit willingness to pay, our aim is to investigate to what extent the hedonic value of luxury consumption contributes to the price premium of luxury brands. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0060)
      In economics, many theories were proposed since Veblen's (1899) analysis of conspicuous consumption to better understand the mechanisms that allow luxury brands to charge high prices for their products. While luxury markets continue to grow all around the world, little experimental research has been done to support those theories. The purpose of this research is to identify whether a presence of a brand label on a luxury good affects willingness to pay. Contrary to hypothetical survey settings used previously on this topic, this experiment is designed to offer real life incentives for revealing the true value people attribute to a brand label with low brand prominence. Using lotteries to elicit willingness to pay, our aim is to investigate to what extent the hedonic value of luxury consumption contributes to the price premium of luxury brands.
    - Oleksiyenko, Anastasiya. How Corruption Affects GDP Recovery?., 2016; 2016-0049; In this paper, we study the linkages between corruption and economic resilience. In particular, our main question is how corruption affects GDP recovery after financial crisis. To study this question empirically, we use a sample of thirty-one economies primarily in Europe, from the period of 2005-2014 which captures the aftermath of the financial crisis of 2007-2009. We apply both the linear model and non-linear effects and conclude that corruption does negatively affect growth in the period of recovery from crisis. Moreover, we find that the crisis puts governance institutions at the risk of underperformance not only in highly bureaucratic but also in moderately bureaucratic economies. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0049)
      In this paper, we study the linkages between corruption and economic resilience. In particular, our main question is how corruption affects GDP recovery after financial crisis. To study this question empirically, we use a sample of thirty-one economies primarily in Europe, from the period of 2005-2014 which captures the aftermath of the financial crisis of 2007-2009. We apply both the linear model and non-linear effects and conclude that corruption does negatively affect growth in the period of recovery from crisis. Moreover, we find that the crisis puts governance institutions at the risk of underperformance not only in highly bureaucratic but also in moderately bureaucratic economies.
    - Salem, Lucia. Ranks or Scores: Does Giving Ordinal Instead of Cardinal Rank Feedback Deter Sabotage?., 2016; 2016-0055; This paper studies unethical behavior under a flat-wage scheme in a lab experiment. I investigate the role of status seeking on effort and sabotage under two different settings: giving cardinal ranks versus giving ordinal ranks. The experiment seeks to study intrinsic competitiveness and was meant to determine which of these two incentive mechanisms induces the most effort and the least sabotage. The results show that there is no difference in amount of sabotage between the different forms of feedback while holding all else constant. When sabotage is introduced, however, giving ordinal rank feedback decreases effort both overall and over time. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0055)
      This paper studies unethical behavior under a flat-wage scheme in a lab experiment. I investigate the role of status seeking on effort and sabotage under two different settings: giving cardinal ranks versus giving ordinal ranks. The experiment seeks to study intrinsic competitiveness and was meant to determine which of these two incentive mechanisms induces the most effort and the least sabotage. The results show that there is no difference in amount of sabotage between the different forms of feedback while holding all else constant. When sabotage is introduced, however, giving ordinal rank feedback decreases effort both overall and over time.
    - Xu, Xinming. An Alternative Model and Experimental Design for Choice Overload, 2017; 2017-0046; Choice overload is a cognitive process in which people have a difficult time making a decision when faced with many options. A variety of experiments have been performed, intending to either prove or disprove the existence of choice overload. Still, there is a mixed result of success in these experiments. This paper attributes the inconsistency of the experimental findings to a lack of clear theoretical framework on this topic, as many theories remain to be largely descriptive and vague. This paper proposes that some consumers suffer from choice overload because they want get the best attributes available and their inability to do so creates dissatisfaction. The description of this mentality is written quantitatively, with the intention of spelling out the assumptions and introducing definitions that have been implied in many previous works. The paper consists of a theoretical section and an experimental design section, which describes the experimental procedures to test the hypotheses derived from the model. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2017-0046)
      Choice overload is a cognitive process in which people have a difficult time making a decision when faced with many options. A variety of experiments have been performed, intending to either prove or disprove the existence of choice overload. Still, there is a mixed result of success in these experiments. This paper attributes the inconsistency of the experimental findings to a lack of clear theoretical framework on this topic, as many theories remain to be largely descriptive and vague. This paper proposes that some consumers suffer from choice overload because they want get the best attributes available and their inability to do so creates dissatisfaction. The description of this mentality is written quantitatively, with the intention of spelling out the assumptions and introducing definitions that have been implied in many previous works. The paper consists of a theoretical section and an experimental design section, which describes the experimental procedures to test the hypotheses derived from the model.
    - Alhassan, Haruna. Tobacco Consumption: Economic Losses to an Indian Household, 2018; 2018-0164 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0164)
      This paper uses survey data from the National Survey of Household Expenditure and Family Welfare from 2009 to 2010, incorporating the Global Adult Tobacco Survey of Indian Households from 2009 to 2010, to investigate how the household expenditure share is affected if there is at least one tobacco consumer in the household. The expenditure shares examined are for food, education, rent and healthcare. My goal is to use a fixed effects model to control for the differences in province. Control variables used are household size, characteristics of household head (gender, education level and occupation), household demographics (whether rural or urban), number of income earners and household facilities (including washing machine, TV, flush toilet and car); in an effort to prove that expenditure shares are allocated differently across provinces. The main finding is that having at least one tobacco consumer in the household results in a negative effect on the expenditure shares of food, education, rent and healthcare. I expect all parameter estimates to be statistically significant except for expenditure shares allocated to the bare necessities, thus basic food items.
    - Alshamsi, Meera Ali. Nudging Individuals to Healthier Decisions, 2018; 2018-0135 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0135)
      The United Arab Emirates, currently the 16th highest country with diabetes, is hoping to lower the high levels of diabetes in the country by 2021. It has been proven that the most common type of diabetes, which is Type 2, can be prevented by behavioral and lifestyle factors. In this study, I aim to test the effectiveness of presenting information, in the form of nudges, to identify whether certain presentation of information will motivate individuals to make better decisions concerning their health. I have collaborated with the UAE Healthy Future Study conducted by the Public Health Research Team at NYUAD to perform an experiment to prove the effectiveness of using the model of nudges in providing information.
    - Arshad, Areeb. Effect of Entering Domestic Partnerships and Marriages on Voting Behavior, 2018; 2018-0119 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0119)
      This paper highlights the importance of considering a new dimension to study the effect of marital status on voting participation in the U.S. Domestic partners vote differently than married couples and these effects vary over age, religious attendance, income, education, ideology, political interest, the presence of a child, and residential mobility. Falling marriage rates and increasing domestic partnerships drive up the salience of domestic partnerships as important family structures in predicting voter turnout. The paper focuses on the differences between domestic partnerships and marriages as it relates to voter turnout. The paper further explores how the effect of various turnout-predictors varies for the two relationship types. The paper shows that domestic partners are more vulnerable to negative effects of low income, low education, the presence of children, high residential mobility, and low religious attendance. The research aims to help create more efficient models to predict voter turnout, voting results, and campaign fund allocation.
    - Bansal, Tanya. CSR Trumped?, 2018; 2018-0115 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0115)
      The triumph of Donald J. Trump as the 45th President of the United States of America on November 8th, 2016 was an unexpected election outcome. This paper examines the impact of the election on stock returns of the Standard and Poor's 500 (S&P500 hereafter) constituent firms, as a function of corporate social responsibility (CSR). I hypothesize that more socially responsible firms underperformed relative to their industry peers in the immediate aftermath of Trump's victory. To this end, I apply an event study based on regression estimation of abnormal returns using both Fama and French Three Factor Model (FF3F) - adjusted returns and Capital Asset Pricing Model (CAPM) - adjusted returns. I find that, contrary to expectation that high CSR firms would be "trumped" or disproportionately punished, the coefficient for the interaction between the event dummy and ESG (Environmental, Social and Corporate Governance) performance is positive and significant, meaning that mean abnormal returns increased with CSR.
    - Chandrasekar, Vishwanath. An Economic Examination of the Bitcoin Network, 2018; 2018-0108 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0108)
      This paper examines the Bitcoin Network through the lens of Economics. The understanding of the backbone of Bitcoin is not as prevalent as knowledge of its recent trends. Through this paper, I will attempt to provide a detailed description of the processes underlying Bitcoin. The paper breaks the process of bitcoin mining into distinct processes - namely the creation of bitcoin and the spending of it. Within these processes, I describe the cryptographic elements of the currency, which in turn lay the foundation for the incentive structures that exist. The cryptographic elements will be approached with a view to describe rather than to discuss the algorithms used. In examining in detail the incentive structures and the strategic scenarios that arise, this paper aims to provide a fuller understanding of the Bitcoin Network.
    - Cierlica, Rafal. The Impact of Transportation Costs on Deforestation in the Democratic Republic of the Congo, 2018; 2018-0154 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0154)
      This article investigates the impact of transportation cost on deforestation in the Democratic Republic of the Congo. Specifically, it assembles a new deforestation data set using satellite imagery and analyses deforestation levels for 193 cities over a period of 16 years. The article then creates a panel data fixed effect model to measure the relationship at question. The results indicate that decreasing transportation cost by 1% increases deforestation by 0.3%. Complementing this main finding the article identifies a data time trend whereby deforestation increases by 0.1% annually. In doing so this article aims to provide data for enabling more informed legislative decisions and reducing the grey area of 'uncertain environmental effects' which often result from new infrastructure projects. The data herewith presented should hopefully aid in guiding a more sustainable and informed approach to Congo's development, one which takes greater care of the Congolese rain forests, currently occupying 46% of Congo's total land area.
    - Ellis, Rhoshenda. The Oil Curse: Oil and Economic Growth, 2018; 2018-0158 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0158)
      This paper seeks to examine the impact that the presence of oil as a natural resource has on the economic growth of a country while taking into consideration the type of governing regime. It hopes to dispel the evidence of the oil curse, which states that oil rents often undermine democracy, and slows down economic growth by promoting corruption and state instability. This research builds on that of Sala-I-Martin's I Just Ran Four Million Regressions by adding oil and political factors to the empirical growth model that he uses. This research employs ordinary least square regression with economic growth as the dependent variable during the period 1990 – 2014. The main findings of this research was that the countries in this dataset show that oil did not have a negative impact on growth even when controlling for the type of political regime in the country during the period.
    - Erkinjonov, Aziz. Sovereign bond spreads in emerging market economies and their macroeconomic fundamentals, 2018; 2018-0142 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0142)
      This paper tests several hypotheses. One is whether the financial crisis of 2008 breaks the link between emerging markets sovereign bond yields and their macroeconomic drivers. The research paper shows that there is a strong correlation between the bond yields and macroeconomic variables such as debt-to-gdp over the period of 2000-2007. It also finds that the effect of debt-to-gdp is statistically insignificant on the sovereign spreads in post-2008.
    - Hamre, Sjur. The Effect of Intensified Import Competition from China on Labor-Market Outcomes and Voter Attitudes in Europe, 2018; 2018-0149 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0149)